"How to Preserve Your Sense of Smell"
Based on a study
of nearly 2,000 people,
our sense of smell
declines as we age,
similar to our loss in vision
and hearing.
About a quarter of Americans
over the age of 50
suffer from
olfactory dysfunction,
a difficulty identifying odors,
which climbs to more than half
of individuals
between the ages
of 65 to 80,
and about 80 percent
in those over the age of 80.
And that was before COVID-19,
which affected the smell
of nearly 50 percent
of sufferers.
Typically, it was temporary,
but as many as a 15 percent
of non-hospitalized
COVID survivors
were still experiencing problems
with the ability to smell
three or more months later,
and there are cases of it
lasting for years.
As anyone with even
a simple head cold can tell you,
when you lose
your sense of smell,
you lose much of your sense
of taste as well.
Between 75 to 95 percent
of what we think of as taste,
may actually be smell.
This was all
too vividly illustrated
by the case
of Algerian War soldiers
whose tongues
were cut out,
remarkably reporting
little loss
of food and drink
flavor sensation.
But hey, if loss of smell
leads to loss of taste,
think of all the weight loss!
That was apparently the thought
behind the development
of a "novel nasal device,"
gag-inducing silicone tubes
you stick into your nostrils
to cordon off
your smell receptors.
Researchers recorded
a drop in preference
for sugary foods and beverages
along with weight loss,
but only among
the younger adults,
presumably because the sense
of smell of the older adults
was already impaired.
Making everything taste bland
may help you skip
a few doughnuts,
but the flipside
is that people
with smelling difficulties
tend to add more salt.
Older individuals
were found to require
two to three times more salt
than those who were younger
to achieve the same salty taste.
It's no wonder
that the lifetime risk
of developing
high blood pressure
may exceed 90 percent.
What can we do to preserve
our sense of smell?
Ambient air pollution
is associated with
olfactory dysfunction,
thought to explain
why nasal biopsies
from residents of Mexico City,
living and dead,
showed more lesions
and inflammatory changes
than those living
in low-pollution cities.
We may not have a choice
where we live,
but there is definitely
a direct source of air pollution
tied to loss of smell
we can all choose to avoid:
cigarette smoke.
Smell loss can have
serious consequences,
for example,
missing a gas leak, smoke,
or spoiled food.
If you have lost your sense
of smell and use natural gas,
please consider buying
a gas detector.
But, in terms of
direct disability,
most people who are affected
don't even to seem to be aware
their smell is impaired,
even when asked directly.
Nearly 8 out of 10 elderly
individuals with smell loss
thought they had
normal smell sensitivity.
Hearing loss, however,
is considered a major cause
of global disability,
ranking among
the top chronic conditions
affecting older adults.
For far too long, though,
as a National Academy
of Medicine report put it,
hearing loss has been
"relegated to the sidelines
of health care."
For those interested,
check out my video series
that starts with Age-Related
Hearing Loss Is Preventable,
then a supplement
shown to help,
and ending with a video
on dietary changes
that can help, too.